funny so john mentioned heidegger
and i'm really interested really really
quite interested in that
um i don't know why my mind jumped to it
so quickly but
it's clearly chomping at the bit so
perhaps it is a good idea to run with it
um though i have no particular
attachment to
following that path at any pace perhaps
it's better to slow down
yeah totally i i uh
a couple things like yeah heidegger's
heidegger's a whole world
like it's a whole world that's i i'm
it's a it's a world that's
there's something that heidegger i think
was um
[Music]
haunted him that
that reveal the level of thinking or
you could say the movement of
intelligibility
right that i started to read
for reasons i don't quite understand at
the same time that circling
was emerging um because my back
my background is i don't have like i'm
not academic
yeah what just really quick that could
you say that another way
uh yeah or at all
um i don't know if i could paraphrase
that completely that was that was um
the dropping in of the realization of
what it would mean to be dealing with
heidegger in the context of a group of
people in a process that actually could
enable that group to have a collective
capacity
yeah yeah and what's interesting and
this is what's telling
about i think revealing about the
the world like what heidegger was doing
is i didn't realize the connection
between the two until like two or three
years later
where because i didn't quite understand
why i was reading heidegger because i
didn't really
understand him i mean i'm dyslexic and i
couldn't learn how to read until i was
like 11 and
took a heroic teacher to kind of do that
for me and
so my reading comprehension is not like
the best
so i don't i didn't quite understand why
i was reading the hardest philosopher
in like like known to man
but there was something about what he
was saying about being that
um that it was like
to to attempt to understand him
what i what i realized was to was to try
to understand him and this is similar to
my experience of actually being mentored
or being with a teacher
that there's this quality of um as roka
would
or as as uh verveiki would say a
participatory
right participation in which like with
the mentor
when my grandfather who was a tailor who
was mentored for two years he lived in a
park in hanover germany when he would
talk about stories about being
dwelling with his mentor there was his
dwelling
quality where much of
much of the learning wasn't so much
about what the
taylor said about tailoring
it was sitting next to him for hours at
a time
right eating all of the sensibility in
the
history of taylor hood and his way of
being
that um you kind of dwell in and then
you kind of come out
in some sense mentored fully through
that
right you kind of carry that way of
being right so
i would imagine it's similar to that
experience of when you go to
a another country and you come back home
and people tell you you have an accent
it's very much like that like for me
that's there's like
what heidegger says and understanding
what he says
and and when people summarize heidegger
there's positions and stuff he takes
but that's actually not that's not
really heidegger heidegger is taking you
on this walk of thinking
right and the point is mostly this is
it's the experience of understanding
that is the thing i was most left with
because though i would like you read
heidegger so you're like trying to like
in order to kind of understand what he's
saying you have to step
so outside of your frame of reference
right to then look
back and then kind of get it and then
just okay start all over again right
yeah and i would just do that hours and
hours and hours and hours and then i go
and circle
and then i do that and i'd circle and i
do that and i'd circle and i do that i'd
circle like this back and forth and then
one day
somebody said something that had this
vernacular
that was just the accent
of circling and it was i'm like
all of a sudden it hit me i'm like very
fun very funny grandfather heidegger
oh i see this betty that what i realized
is he taught me actually how to see
um he taught me where like he taught me
that there's like you could say
the phenomenological
sense is is this this awareness of that
concealment
is and that that that which is most
concealed is that which is most near
and that and that that kind of looking
of getting that sense of a horizon or a
talos
and also the background and the
foreground
and just having the sense of just
following that back
got kind of closer and closer and closer
in which is
in i would say encircling started to
cultivate this deep sense of wonder
right about what i think the way that um
verveiki talks about is this
transframing this primordial ground
which when you when you
realize it there's this kind of
primordial sense of
wonderment that comes up that is also
the very
experience of when you participate with
each other in that sense of wonderment
um
it seems to it seems to produce the kind
of experiences
that people call wonder and love
and affinity and unreasonable
devotion and you know
yeah um wow
well i'm not sure if
um
one thing that
was running through my
way of making sense of what was what i
was perceiving
um was the sense or the
feeling of a
like a space-time okay okay i can say it
this way
um i had a real i had it inside a long
time ago where
i had realized if you take a look at a
light at a lightning bolt
and from the perspective of a person
looking at a lightning bolt it looks
jaggedy but from the perspective of the
lightning bolt it's a perfectly straight
line
because we're looking at it from what
you might call a neutral third person
perspective through
space it's perceiving the galvanic
potential so it's proceeding along the
the uh the gradient of galvanic
potential and
is simply following the straightest path
through the gradient galvanic potential
yeah um so from its perspective it's
traversing a straight line
yeah and then i was imagining the notion
of a circle
the circle ling but a circle and the
circle
has a from a again objective
third-person space-time perspective i
can say that you're in a circle when
there are a group of people oriented
i would imagine in a uh all facing
inward
geometrically yeah all the same place at
the same time yeah right
yeah but then i was having this flash of
for example
when i was reading um manuel delanda
actually that book right there and how
it connected with
a conversation that i had been having in
my head of course with
je de louis and there was a flash of
insight as the two connected
and i had this feeling of it being as if
we were in a circle
but mediated through
a phenomenology that has a different
frame of reference yeah that makes sense
yeah it does can you say more about the
frame of reference
yeah oh man um
well if we if we just zoom in on the
conversation we're having right now
yeah and i can feel myself getting lost
so if i get lost please bring me back
um what what we can notice is that
there's a very fun objective illusion
that we're having a conversation with
each other
um in some sense this is as if we were
face to face
separated by a couple of feet yeah um
and yet of course if i notice what's
happening in reality
it couldn't be further from the truth in
fact it's quite likely that
the sound waves that are being projected
into my microphone electrically and
converted into
digital signals inside my laptop
packeted
up in tcp packets and then spewed across
the internet
through the protocol that may in fact be
jumping through satellites into space
and back down
which then are emerged converted into
analog signals in your laptop
um the medium that enables that
creates a so think about that like the
lightning bolt there's a
objective perspective on our point of
view that collapses that entire
complexity of the underlying reality of
what packet space would perceive as a
hell of a job
into something that is isomorphic to a
face-to-face conversation
yeah right yeah so if i can run that
same projection here and simulate a
face-to-face conversation using a medium
you know a variety of different media
constructs i could do the inverse
and i could say oh well it looks like
the medium of capitalists and producing
books and shipping them to me via amazon
and
projecting text into my eyeball that was
glued to paper
i uh memetically copying the text that
was actually scripted by
uh in this case de lloys and de landa
over a different time frame
same exact thing in reverse and so in
point of fact i am actually in a circle
with them but that circle is propagating
through reality in a different kind of
way and if we can actually grok
the consequences of the media on the way
the consciousness is actually able to
form itself as a coherent singularity
then we're doing something interesting
[Laughter]
hey i don't think i got lost i actually
pulled it off
you really did pull it off yeah totally